Tufts War Museum Collection UA208
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts War Museum Collection
1813 -- 1935
1900 -- 1928
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts College
Tufts War Museum
UA208
4.08 Linear Feet 6 boxes, 1 oversized folder
Arrangement
This collection is organized in three series: Museum cabinet artifacts; Museum artifacts, posters and bonds; and World War I Photographs and Postcards.
Custodial History
This collection was created after finding two wooden artifact boxes in the vault of Ballou Hall in 2010. The artifacts and their labels indicated that they had once belonged to the Tufts War Relics Museum, also known as the Tufts War Museum or Tufts College War Relics Museum, about whose existence DCA had only known through Tufts Weekly articles from 1919-1920. Upon transfer to DCA and further research into the original contents of the collection, WWI posters were moved from the AC collection to this collection.
Most of the original museum artifacts are still missing: according to contemporary articles, the museum included collections sent by Dr. Arthur Irving Andrews (including a section of the barbed wire used in the defenses of the famous fort at Douaumont, shells from Verdum, lead bullets, stones from the Verdun battle field, two horsechestnuts from a tree which though badly scarred was still alive in Verdun), Professor A. C. Lane, Professor H. V. Neal (most likely the Y. M. C. A. material given his service during the war), Dr. W. F. Waytt (including Austrian and Italian helmets, an Austrian trench spade, several bombs, torpedoes, hand-grenades, trench mortar type), by J. C. Geer '18 (pictures of war scenes in Siberia), by Dr. McLean (hand grenade), by W. B. Richardson (four hand grenades), by E. A. Terhune '17, Talbot, J. B. Kellock '20, Donald MacKenzie '21 of the Tufts Ambulance Unit, and a German Flag and war posters from France and Germany secured through Dean Anthony from Raymond Bon of the Tufts Engineering School. The flag was one which formerly flew over the Kaiser's War College on the Rhine and was taken down at the time of the march of YD, 26th Division, through Engers.
Undergraduate and Alumni and Alumnae organizations of Tufts collaborated in obtaining items for the collection.
Biographical / Historical
According to a 1920 Tufts Weekly article, Professor Arthur Irving Andrews, head of the Department of History and Public Law, founded the Tufts War Museum in 1919.
The Tufts War Relics Museum, also known as the Tufts War Museum or Tufts College War Relics Museum, was originally and temporarily set up in the library at Ballou Hall with Ms. Hayes acting as custodian and Dr. A. I. Andrews, professor of history and public law, as curator. Tufts students, alumni and alumni and alumnae organizations, and faculty donated items (primarily from Austria, France, Germany, Italy, and Russia) and the US War Department provided military transportation service for shipping items from Europe to Tufts.
In November 1919, a special exhibit of the Tufts War Museum was set up in Ballou Hall (third floor) in connection with the meetings of the Tufts College Teachers' Association and the New England History Association on the Hill. It is currently unknown how long the museum actually existed.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes a few of the war-related artifacts from the original Tufts War museum established after World War I. Materials include photographs, including tintypes; postcards; fossils, shells, and stones; coins; memorabilia; posters; and other artifacts.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Related Materials
Arthur Irving Andrews Papers, 1911 -- 1978. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.
Melville S. Munro papers, 1858-1959. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.
Academic Support -- Libraries, Galleries, Archives; Alumni and Alumni Relations
- Museum cabinet artifacts, 1813 -- 1935; 1914 -- 1919; UA208.001; 1.25 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains objects from and artifact cabinet found in the Ballou vault in summer 2010. These artifacts were originally part of the collection of the Tufts University Museum of War and most of them are from Germany and France. The majority of these artifacts are from World War I, and include bronze medallions commemorating battles and events; uniform accessories including buttons, shoulder straps, ribbons, cockades and pins; shrapnel; lighters; and jewelry. A number of these artifacts still have their original museum labels attached. These provide colloquial descriptions of the items and their origins. The artifact cabinet also included a rock collection of unknown relation and origin, which was included in this series because one of the items was a shard of a stained window of Chartre Cathedral. Specific descriptions of individual relics can be found in the notes field at the item level.
  Artifacts were kept together and described by cabinet tray. If necessary, individual cataloging can be done in the future.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as found.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Commemorative medallions, 1916 -- 1923; UA208.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    This grouping includes 16 commemorative brass medallions dating from approximately 1916 to 1923. The majority of the objects appear medals commemorating specific WWI battles in France. Included are medallions from Alsace, St. Mihiel (1918), Strasbourg (1917), and Verdun (1916 and 1917). There are also two medals featuring images of Joan of Arc (Jeanne d'Arc "Liberatrice du Territoire" and Johanne d'Arc), one medal featuring President Woodrow Wilson, one medal stating, "Reconnaissance," and another stating "Heroisme, ici le Barbares Sont Passes." Three medals feature only images. The items vary in shape. Some are circular, while others are rectangles, and one is in the shape of a cross.
  - Shrapnel, mezuzah, spearhead, coins, lighter, cigarette case, shoulder strap, 1918; UA208.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
    This grouping includes 11 items. Descriptions of the artifacts are as follows:
    A) shrapnel; B) 2 pieces of shrapnel [with labels]; one from anti-aircraft gun in Ludwigshafen (1918); one cut from the knee of a Yankee soldier in Neuilly (1918); C) cigarette case from Cathedrale Reims; D) mezuzah; E) spearhead from a French archaeologist [with label]; F) Woodrow Wilson lighter from France; G) shoulder strap from uniform; also included are two shells (in envelopes) and a large rock.
  - Buttons, coins, pendants, lighter, 1918 -- 1930; UA208.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
    This grouping includes 8 items. These items are contained in a smaller box within grouping 00001. Descriptions of the artifacts are as follows:
    A) 2 buttons from US uniforms; B) coin and ring; coin from Passionspiele Oberammergau (1930); C) coin/pendant from American Independence centennial celebration (1926); D) Polish pendant depicting Jesus "wonder child"; E) 2 unlabelled rock fragments; F) Lighter with messages "en avant" and "fleury Thiamont."
  - Pins, buttons, patch, bracelet, ribbons, shoulder strap, 1914 -- 1919; UA208.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
    This grouping includes 21 items originally found in drawer #3. Descriptions of the artifacts are as follows:
    A) 3 German pins; Deutschland ueber alles [Germany above everything] (1914-15); Mit reinem Gewissen und reiner Hand 4. Aug ergreifen wir das Schwert [On the 4th of Aug we gripped the sword with clear conscience and a clean hand] (1914); Gold gab ich fuer Eisen [I gave gold for iron]; B) pin with image of "Germany fighting Russia (the bear) and Allies (7-headed Hydra), Somme-Kapathen (1919)" [with label]; C) pin from the Australian Commonwealth Military Forces; D) 3 uniform buttons (German, French, American); E) 2 uniform buttons (Russian (1919), Bolshevik) [with labels]; F) YMCA pin; G) US pin; H) American id bracelet; I) 3rd Army patch; J) 4 ribbon bars; K) cross medal; L) Kaiserparade ribbon; M) shoulder strap "from dead German" [with label].
    All quoted material is from the relic's corresponding label.
  - Pins, cockades, 1900 -- 1919; UA208.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
    This grouping includes 10 items originally found in drawer #3. Descriptions of the artifacts are as follows:
    A) 2 New Zealand pins; B) cockade of the South African Union (1919) [with label]; C) S. Lancashire pendant from prisoner of war [with label]; D) "Shoulder insignia of a Siamese" [with label] (1919); E) pin with message: "Qui s'y Frotte s'y Brule" [Who rubs against it gets burned] motto of Lorraine [with label]; F) South African cockade (1900-1902) [with label]; G) pin with message: der Koenig rief und alle alle kamen [The King cried and everyone everyone came] (1914); H) 2 pins; one with helmet; one from the Order of the Black Eagle with the message: suum cuique [to each their own].
  - Papyrus bought in Syracuse, 1914; UA208.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
    This item was originally in drawer #3.
  - Pins, labels, tin type photographs, medallion, 1813 -- 1914; UA208.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
    A) medallion stating: Siege de Paris (1870-1871), Emploi des Aerostats pour la defense de Paris; B) 4 metal backed photographs probably tin types from the Civil War (judging from uniform) with identical images of one boy, many the same as in box 004; C) labels with no corresponding artifacts; D) potential fragment of inventory list with dates; E) 3 pins; one with Austro-hungarian flag and German flag and the message: Einigkeit macht stark [Unity creates strength] (1914); one with message: Mit Gott fuer Koening and Vaterland [With God for the King and the Fatherland] (1813); and one ribbon (black, white, yellow, red).
  - Coins, sea horse, gum, locket, papyrus, lighter, ring, daguerreotypes, 1914 -- 1935; UA208.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
    This grouping includes 33 items. Descriptions of the artifacts are as follows:
    A) Iron Cross (1914) and coin with message: O crux ave spes unica (O hail to the cross, our only hope); B) plaster piece and medallion commemorating the erection of the Lafayette memorial in Brooklyn, NY (1917); C) gum buried in sand from Africa [with label]; D) sea horse from St. Briar [with label]; E) pin from Universite de Grenoble; F) blue locket with photographs; the front says Marken in gold letters [could be a keepsake from Marken a seaside town in the Netherlands]; G) book-shaped lighter (French); H) coin from Boston Common Centennial (1935) and "Gold gab ich fuer Eisen" (I gave gold for iron) ring; I) papyrus [with label] (1935); J) 13 small metal-backed photographs probably tin types from the Civil war (judging from uniform), many the same as in box 003; K) small metal Egyptian animal sculpture; this grouping also contains 2 rocks, 4 shells, one long piece of shrapnel [with label] and a label with no associated artifact (transcribed for preservation purposes).
  - Rock collection, glass from Verdun cathedral, chop sticks, 1885 -- 1928; UA208.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
    This grouping includes a rock collection found in one drawer of the artifact cabinet that held the remaining War Museum artifacts. It is unknown if this rock collection has any relation to the Tufts War Museum. There are approximately 32 rock speciments in the collection. Some are fossils. When found, this drawer had two labels, one states: Matlock Bath 1885, the second states: Hampton Court July 1928. It is unknown which rocks, if any, these labels correspond to. These labels have been transcribed and can be found in an envelope in this box. There were also two labeled boxes in this drawer that likely contain more artifacts relevant to the War Museum collection. According to their labels, these boxes contained glass from the Verdun Cathedral and pebbles from Capri (1912). The labels have been transcribed onto acid-free paper and are grouped with the corresponding artifacts. This drawer also contained a pair of dark brown chop sticks.
- Museum artifacts, posters and bonds, 1914 -- 1918; UA208.002; 0.0 Linear Feet
  This series includes World War I artifacts donated to the museum. Bonds and Posters from World War I in the artifact collection were reassigned to this series because they most likely had been part of the original collection, contemporary Tufts Weekly articles report of such items, and because the AC collection is not provenance-based..
  This series is not arranged.
  - Department of the Treasury World War I bond posters, 1914 -- 1918; UA208.002.006.00003 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 6)
    Posters removed from map case (room 10), drawer #23. "Lend Your Money to Your Government, Buy a United States Government Bond Second Liberty Loan of 1917" [US Treasury Building]
    "Buy Liberty Bonds, Third Liberty Loan, Starts April 6th, Buy Today at Any Bank 1918" [calendar in color]
    "A. Kriegsanleihe" [thunder cloud with a lighting bolt striking a building] "Help Him Win by Saving and Serving, Buy War-Savings Stamps" [color picture of two children shaking hands with a soldier] (2 copies)
    "Pour le Retour Souscrivez, 4.e Emprunt National, Credit Foncier d'Algerie et de Tunisie, 43 Rue Cambon, Paris." [people looking out at ships entering the harbor while a plane flies overhead.]
    "3.e Emprunt de la Defense National, Credit Lyonnais, Souscrivez" [color picture of a soldier with a flag that says Liberte. The soldier is standing over the globe.]
    "Credit Commercial de France, 4eme Emprunt de la Defense National, 1918, Souscrivez Pour la Victoire et Pour le Triomphe de la Liberte" [color picture of soldiers going to battle. Image of a woman in a loin cloth and a wreath in her left hand and a knife in her right hand.]
    "Un Dernier Effort et on l'aura, Imp. Cornille Serre, Paris" [picture of 5 US soldiers and 1 unknown soldier climbing a rock with a vulture standing on them]
    "Sure! We'll Finish the Job. Victory Liberty Loan. 1918" [color picture of a man in overalls swinging his arm.]
    "Attenti, Il Serpente Tetesco e Preso! Bisogna ora strappargli i denti del. Beleno! [Corners of poster are missing. Hand choking the neck of a snake. On the snake are German cross symbols.]
    "Americans All! Honor Roll: Du Bois, Smith, O'Brien, Cegka, Haucke, Pappandrikopolous, Andrassi, Billotto, Levy, Turovich, Kowalski, Chriczanevicz, Knutson, Gonzalez. Victory Liberty, 1917" [Woman in a white dress holding a wreath in front of an American flag.]
    "Joan of Arc Saved France, Save Your Country, Buy War-Saving Stamps" [Joan of Arc holding a sword on a blue background.]
    "Finish the Job, Subscribe to the 'Victory' Liberty Loan" [Initial V surrounded by laurels, yellow background]
    "Buy, Buy, Buy! Victory Liberty Loan" [red, white and blue]
    "Show Your Button, Victory Liberty Loan" [blue background with white text]
    "Clear the Way!! Buy Bonds, Fourth Liberty Loan" [Woman in front of an American flag. Below her, men load a machine. Poster in pieces]
    "Save-Buy-- for Victory, for sale here" [blue-black text on white background]
    "Invest in the Victory Liberty Loan" [description for photo "They kept the sea lanes opened." Picture of a submarine and other ships. Very fragile and edges are torn.]
    "On les aura! 2E. Emprunt de la Defense Nationale, Sousrivez." [Soldier gesturing on a white background]
    "Buy United States Government War-Savings Stamps, Your Money Back with Interest from the United States Treasury" [picture of people buying war-saving stamps and smiling at a child waving the flag]
    "For Victory, Buy War Bonds, Fourth Liberty Loan" [large poster, tri-folded and in fragile condition. Woman wielding a sword and shield in front of the American flag and eagle; she's flying over soldiers.]
    "Avanti Savoia!!..." [Small Print, torn on the side. Italian soldier shouting.]
    "Remember-Argonne, Chateau-Thierry, St. Mihiel, Eelleau Wood, Cantigny, Soissons, Vesle, C_ _ rge-And Invest, Victory Liberty Loan, Women's Liberty Loan Committee. [Stylized version of Greek goddess Athena; illegible names behind her image]
    "Hun or Home? Buy More Liberty Bonds" [young woman holding a baby with lurking, dangerous figure behind her, black and white]
    World War, 1914-1918; poster
  - Department of the Treasury World War I bond posters, 1914 -- 1918; UA208.002.006.00004 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 6)
    Posters removed from map case (room 10), drawer #23. Invest [blue V on red rectangle with white and blue border]. Bring It Again by US Government Bonds Third Liberty Loan [liberty bell]. Fight or Buy Bonds Third Liberty Loan 1917 [liberty holding flag in front of charging soldiers]. The Hun-His Mark Blot It Out with Liberty Bonds [bloody handprint]. Buy Early Victory Liberty Loan [white letters on red background] 2 posters. My Daddy Bought Me a Government Bond of the Third Liberty Loan. Did Yours? [small girl holding liberty bond]. Finish the Job, Subscribe to the Victory Liberty Loan [blue V with laurel wreath on yellow background with green border]. Help the Hun, Buy US Government Bonds Third Liberty Loan [US soldier pushing a Hun back from a kneeling woman and child]. Remember Belgium, Buy Bonds Fourth Liberty Loan [German soldier pulling adolescent girl on green background with flames]. Boys and Girls, You can Help Your Uncle Sam Win the War, Save Your Quarters, Buy War-Saving Stamps [Uncle Sam with adolescent boy and girl]. For Home and Country, Victory Liberty Loan [US soldier with arm around wife and holding small male child]. Save Your Child from Autocracy and Poverty, Buy War-Saving Stamps [toddler in front of the torch of Liberty]. Buy, Buy, Buy, Victory Liberty Loan [red, white and blue stripes]. Save and Invest in the Safest, Simplest Security, Buy War-Saving Stamps, circa 1918 [blue and black text on white background]. Cacciali Via! Sottoscrivete al Prestito. [soldier defending peasant woman and child]. "Fate tutti il vostro dovere!" Le sottoscrizioni al prestito si ricevono press il credito italiano [soldier pointing at view; very large and in two pieces]. Per la patria i miei occhi! Per la pace il vostra denaro. [soldier with bandaged head and eyes]. Why Germany wants peace now. [red and black text around basic map of Europe labeled The Prussian Blot]. Help our town win this flag. Fourth Liberty Loan [honor flag with honor roll of subscribers]. Sempre avanti!! [woman leading six soldiers]. The best investment on Earth! War-Saving Stamps. [uncut sheet of postcard-sized ads] 2 posters. Joan of Arc saved France. Women of America save your country. Buy War-Saving Stamps [Joan of Arc brandishing sword on blue background]. [Half of a war bonds poster]. To make the world a decent place to live in, do your part. Buy US Government bonds. Third Liberty Loan [soldiers on red background with gray border]. The Liberty Digest. Liberty Map of the Western Front of the Great World War [map of Europe from August 5, 1918]. Map fragment of Maine. Come on! Buy more liberty bonds. [soldier with bayonet over dead enemy]. Keep him free. Buy War-Saving stamps [American bald eagle behind US fighter planes]. The American creed [blue text on white with red border].
    poster
- World War I photographs and postcards, UA208.004; 0.25 Linear Feet
  This series includes postcards and photographs collected by Thomas Whittemore during World War I. Were likely part of the Tufts War Museum. Index refers to Italian postcards which are currently missing. They were removed from Memory Books collection in October 2011.
  This series is arranged according the index included in the series.
  - [Photographs index], UA208.004.007.00001 (Box Shared 130)
  - [American Cards], UA208.004.007.00002 (Box Shared 130)
  - [French Postcards], UA208.004.007.00003 (Box Shared 130)
  - [Airplane photographs], UA208.004.007.00004 (Box Shared 130)
  - [Group photographs], UA208.004.007.00005 (Box Shared 130)
  - [Russian Front], UA208.004.007.00006 (Box Shared 130)
  - [Various Individual Officers], UA208.004.007.00007 (Box Shared 130)
  - [Japanese Postcards], UA208.004.007.00008 (Box Shared 130)
  - [Miscellaneous], UA208.004.007.00009 (Box Shared 130)